consciousness mind and thoughts how
would you define conscience in this
simplest possible but accurate terms
okay so consciousness so kind of what it
so consciousness so kind of what it
means for me is the fact that there are
things so I tend to see like like
like
there's something rather than nothing
I'm kind of aligned so it's um you know
she does I mean the object is around you
anything so where's the consciousness
what is it consciousness a sort of
negative in regard to that it's like
that and and it can only be I uh I sort
of think of it as just the fact that I'm
alive because if there weren't it if
there was nothing to be discerned nobody
no consciousness but because there are
things to be discerned its consciousness
so you can only see the consciousness
through the things that
so if you first if your first point of
relationship your conscience is the
better you're alive does that change is
that sort of give rise to something else
in its own place some other more
specific consciousness was something
like that
oh you mean so okay so yeah then you
could you could then within the funnel
you're alive you can then look at you
can then discern that things appear in
different ways or in different places
different domains so all of that is then
on account of you being alive what's the
level of being alive yes the level of
death of all I said before so it just
the fact that there are things rather so
it's given yeah yeah yeah it's not it's
not something you're saying yeah which
is quite different to the idea the
common idea of what consciousness is I
am conscious in my mind in my in my
brain yeah you know in the scientist
even you know try to find the Center for
consciousness in the brain yes
so it's this thing with my awareness or
whatever else that comes with that yeah
with the same characteristics of being
alive being present being discerning oh
that's within this body within this
within within my head within within my
mind but it isn't isn't it no because
all of that within internally externally
is only distinguished on the basis of
you being alive in the first place and
that's already with consciousness says
yeah that's what we refer to this
conscious body yeah the body is already
there conscious nothing to do with you
so defy the body is there means
consciousness is there were they you
can't have the body and then the
consciousness discerned later so it's
more inseparable from it's more accurate
to say that the consciousness is
with the things that your conscious self
well that's a thing the things you're
conscious of our own can only be done at
the base of your body yeah exactly so
it's more secular thing to say it is
called like body it Smith the father
yeah and that's what what's left for in
our hunt and this conscious body and
everything else that kind of appears
within that external to him yeah but no
not like like it's something to be found
in the body or no or separate from the
body yeah you cannot address or attend to or
yeah you cannot address or attend to or
look at your consciousness independent
of the experience at all as you know if
the conscious body but we're basically
the body that this consciousness yes
this consciousness that we've already
caught up so it's no it's really a
problem with consciousness is that it's
it's it's something people don't think
yeah which already you know comes from
the assumptions that you have about that
mean internally external world our
consciousness isn't this sand but if you
look what any of that any of those such
distinctions or discriminations so to
speak a possible one because you're
alive in the first place being alive
means having body there's alive yeah
which is a conscious body yeah body with
consciousness probably bereft of
consciousness yeah which I didn't ask
for exactly so the division of you
internally in your mind internally and
in the world external in the sense
objects external is not the division of
the body and the consciousness yeah it's
the division is within the conscious
body yeah so what do you look internally
the conscious bodies there where do you
look externally the countries what is
there when do you look both neither
conscious body has to be there anything
is there yeah there's a conscious body
exist yeah yeah that's it even if the
most abstract thought or when people say
oh I had this out-of-body experience yes
on account of the conscious body they
don't really argue the body experience
other the body experiences
like actually out of the pot experience
payable you can't show anybody any bond
I guess would be honored as in when you
were not just dead yes but you're an
earthen beforehand yeah and then the
body disintegrates and then there will
be but they would constitute an
experience anymore no so you wouldn't be
out of default experience it's a
contradiction terms out of the body
experience because any experience known
to you even in the art of like utmost
fantasy in abstraction is on account of
the conscious body
so saying experience out of the body
means experience independent of the body
and that's impossible to experience and
even if you don't discern the body which
is much the time and the most people
know in most cases you have an
experience and you're not aware of the
body as you're having that experience
that doesn't change your face and change
the fancy body is there and you can be
aware of it because it's there yeah and
that's where you could develop the
knowledge in any given time guitars
exactly if if for somebody who's not
aware that the body is there and they
kind of don't even think about it and
develop the sense of Independence or
well just ask yourself would my thoughts
that are completely divorced from the
body pay no attention to body and even think
pay no attention to body and even think
the body second kudos thoughts remain if
I get killed next second next moment
absolutely not and you know that it's
just you ignore that necessary the
fundamental dependence of anything
mental on account of the physical yeah
and these are servings in the body and
the body is the ultimate well that's
already a mental notion yeah on account
of the country yeah so if you look at
the mental it will be undermined by
physical if you look at physical it's on
demand by the
exactly so consciousness means then
having a body that is alive that's it
yeah how would you then again in simple terms
how would you then again in simple terms
but accurate and define the mind so
things are always significant things
always meaningful so I'm always in a
kind of situation which I can describe
in terms of my mood or just how I
understand what's going on
so everything anything I attend to is
always within a context Thanks
it's always within the mood yeah that's
one dude yeah but I always had to you
always have to have a mood but also just
the fact that things are understood in
relation to other things
oh yeah sure sure so yeah so that just
that within which is which is within a
mood yeah yeah your interaction with
things he's always within the mood so even if
he's always within the mood so even if
you assume that you're the same
principle even if you pay no attention
to the mood yeah or just thirty means
there yeah then I wouldn't so but I
wouldn't say so so I'm in a mood and
that's one way in which I can the mind
come you know so the mind is that more
general capacity or like a phenomenon
whereby everything is experience within
a moon so what would the relationship
between the mood in the country's body
what's the relationship well that both
given their both I'm subjected to both
of them are both simultaneously present
between them maybe I guess the body so
it comes first
well partly because the satavahanas the
body comes first but also
well the mood primary that's the thing
that's the thing so I you know I used to
think I think you know the standard way
of thinking is you notice yourself in a
mood I'm not answering the question I'm
kind of just going off my notes right
and you notice you in a mood and then
you think oh that's probably because I'm
let's say I'm let's say I'm feeling
agitated or something and then you go
and you notice all I've got because I'm
thinking about all these things
I said I'll stop thinking about all
these things and then I'll changed then
I'll be able to that agitation will go
away and of course that's the wrong way
around there are all those thoughts that
I'm because I recognize that recognize
because of the agitation the agitation
comes first
and they said therefore there's nothing
I can do to get rid of agitation because
everything I can do is get is part of
within this mood so so it's the same
that's the same sort of structure as the
body in that it's like The Container
Photon but you're asking what's the
relationship between those two between
the countries border punches bottom loot
and the mood you describe the relation
between the mood in the thoughts which
would have been my next question okay as
in consciousness mind thoughts yeah it's
it's the same principle yeah all these
all thoughts are always within a mood
mood is always within a body
exactly yeah so it's not that the mood
comes first but that's the thing
practically for a mind it's not freed
from ignorance what comes first is the
within thoughts you get to discern the
mood yeah obviously if you don't abandon
the lack of understanding and they got
to the nature of the right order you
will then still think the thoughts come
first and then blame blames them for
your moods and for everything else
exactly so your thoughts come first
ready to speak because that's very
ignorant you've taken here that's your
starting point but we didn't tell you
this in the mood initially you discerned
a mood
thoughts you name the thoughts you tried
to stop thinking thoughts or meditation
technique they will prevent you from
thinking so you don't get into bed with
yeah but then if you appointed rightly
you get to understand it thoughts and
simultaneously present mood it's
actually the mood comes first
structurally so to speak
they're very at the same time but the
mood is more general amorous mood is
more from fundamentals so basically
there's nothing I can do in regard to
these thoughts will get below that mu
that moves or step outside of it exactly
yeah yeah whatever you do anybody
direction I do on those thoughts is all
within that mood yeah I'm calm and
that's what we've been doing about so
yeah so so extensively like the things
you can attend to things you can think
about yeah and then the peripheral in
regarded first you do some prefer a
secondary to it but then you realize no
peripheral is that container
the primary container yeah so that's how
you get to get the sign of the mind
yeah that's what's just gonna say that's
the mind you discerned assignment in
mind in regard to your thoughts in the
unitary like actual present experience
if you attend so that's why it's such a
wrong view to think you can attend to
your mind in the same sense you attend
to other objects including your thoughts
because thoughts are mental objects yes
object so the mental said I can attend
to in the same sense the sights and
objects of the visual sense yeah so
there's thought many thoughts going on
some thoughts of peripherals
there are peripheral thoughts that sure
but but the mind is something is that
thing that's the sort of background of
those thoughts that I cannot attend to
so that's the thing so you as I said you
start you have to start first with
thoughts then discern the mind yeah
rightly the right ordered in mind is
that which is the first thoughts a
secondary so any movement on my thought
in regard to my mood is within the mood
yeah so it's the sermon of the mood they
will free you from the mood not the
particular set of movements of your
thoughts yeah and then you can go
further following the same principle
once you get established in that notion
of your own mind that peripherals sign
the peripheral container of what the
mood is you also then get to see what
peripheral to that so can I just what is
the necessary basis for having any
regardless of the thoughts they might be
moving within it being alive and you
realize that is the peripheral container
to your mood yeah that was fast exactly
that doesn't disappear when you go down
to this lower level so that it just
stays there the only thing he what
happens to you gets ignored yeah the
right order gets ignored and that's why
you jump into assuming the wrong go but
it's possible for it not to be because
it is always it always that it's
implicit in the mood which implicitly I
thought it's always that yeah it's
always you come it's the closest thing
to you if you understood that it can't
not be there then you wouldn't forget
that it was impossible to forget it is
there because forgetfulness is within
them yeah it's determined by being alive
that's where you can forget can i KY say
something out like I used to think I
used to and I found it helpful to think
of the mind as being like the light in
the room I'm looking at you now
and I can't see the light not something
I can see and yeah I kind of tend to the
light another thing things but I know
the fine so it's not that I've not
really doubt about whether you have to
think about it I don't have to think
about it yeah no that's yeah
that's the dead implication then I said
the mind is implicit in the thoughts in
as much conscious body is implicit
within the mind within the thoughts can
you even conceive looking even
perceiving the light if you have no eyes
and no body
so that kind of leads to then the final
point so through your thoughts you
discern a mood you stop regarding the
second you see there's more primordial
simultaneously enduring the fundamental
container of those thoughts within that
you descend further necessary basis for
your thoughts for your mind which is the
conscious body body with consciousness
out there nothing to do with you he has
a rose he was born given you're fully
within it fully subjected to its nature
isn't that a thought yeah but it's a
thought that's made possible yeah but
okay so can you experience a conscious
body in any other manner than having a
thought of it can you experience
anything without that thing being also
thought there no being without that
thing being fundamentally from Maruyama
container the same thought impossible so
what's the difference then from the
starting point of origin as thoughts and
then the point after you you understand
the relationship between the nature of
the mind the nature of the conscious
body and then you do as well it's the
same thought well it's just ink seeing
the difference between the thought and
and the thought ender thought well okay
well see those thoughts those thoughts
resist you you know you find them there
you're subjected to those thoughts so
best sort of that's their externality
sort of thing thing there's something
beyond me well that is another thought
but when I like it's a notion of beyond
me
yeah it's another thought yeah yeah but
it's not really beyond but if you but
let's let's like again restart okay so
you have a you have thoughts of
agitation whatever then you recognize
the unpleasant mood of dead vegetation
yeah and you stop disordering it so to
speak you stop regarding the mood as a
product of your thoughts when you see
the movements of your thoughts are
within the container the mood which is
why they move yeah geez why they shuffle
and try to get shake off the mood dead
already frees you from the pressure of
the thoughts by discerning the right
order of those thoughts so the thought
of the mood is a thought the thought of
the agitation within the mood that you
want to get rid of is another thought
yeah so the difference is just wanted to
get rid of it all no I want to give you
and why do you want to get rid of it
what is the necessary condition for
wanting to get what is that's the
condition for craving thankful failing
okay but something in regards to the
painful feeling what's the nested
condition because you know you can
remove the craving is still have painful
feeling but what is it that you cannot
have if you remove the craving
like the assumption of the wrong god Oh
si okay you will not be trying to get
rid of it unless you assume that you can
get carried away by getting rid of so
the movements you engage a routine in
the assumption - you can buy the moving
can get rid of it by understanding the
order by seeing the order in the right
way that's completely pointless so
that's why like if you say theoretically
yes you just thought yes everything is
just thought in a sense that yeah it
tell me about the physical conscious
body yeah but we did the thoughts there
is the right order of the thoughts yeah
there is the right nature and there is
the wrong word and that's the sole
difference between a protrusion and
another hand
that's what I mean like oh you go you
get to understand you moved on account
of thoughts then you get to understand
the necessary basis for both moon and
the thoughts they move within the mood
is this conscious body and then you
abandon it to understanding the nature
which is yet you were subjected to you
given you have no say on the level of
the elements pretty much yeah
and then you realize oh some back onto
the thoughts and that's what foreigner
hunt in the in the in what's thought
there is only things they've been
thought yeah in the scene there's just a
scene in the thought that is just a
thought in the herd there's just a herd
because it can't be anything else but
see in the scene there is just the scene
means in the scene there is no more
wrong order of the scene in the thought
there is no more wrong order of the
thought so literally in the scene that
is just seen there is nothing else there
for Kota Gina there is the whole world
of difference there the world that's not
outside of the scene yeah whoa result of
the scene it's just the word the world
that's the result of the wrong order of
the scene or the thought of any other
sense so basically getting the order right
so basically getting the order right
changes the significance of things well
I'm getting the order right basically
means Singh prevents the gratuitous
maintenance to the sense of
yeah the sense of self the sense of
conceit but what I mean is like everyone
can say oh I know the thought is yeah
but get the right order then when you
use well there would be a surgery when
you say thought you're talking about
what the Buddha meant when he said
thought yeah yeah hey said that's a
different thing
no that's that's funny so that's what
people say like they would read a suit
that and then oh yeah okay yeah yeah so
sure you understand it some level but
then you have to see understanding this
what is that result in what are the
symptoms of having understand having
that having this understood what are the
symptoms of that
well symptom is you're enabled means
you're unable to suffer means you have
destroyed birth aging sickness anything
that you subtract it you cannot possibly
disturb any but completely effortless
indifference equanimity is not something
you must latch on to yeah it's the
result of your understanding so you're
after the unshakable as a result of your
understanding so do you still think you
understood the thought yeah and and
that's always the main problem it's not
really like I don't have the right
thoughts and it's like thinking it that
you have understood that which you
haven't yeah to that degree
you won't make it understand exactly so
as I mean yes you read a suitor it makes
sense and you think understood
consciousness you think you understood
mine you think understood the thought
and just you just need to tidy it up a
bit more if you understood any of those
for what it is if you understood what
thought within a thought is in thought
that is just a thought you would be
another so then no matter had well no
I'm not so I said something for granted
my understanding of this I have an
understanding of it which gives me
direction and I could yeah well because
it makes sense to me I can think that's
right but actually it makes sense to me
it's not right so that's with me like
you like person interesting practice
should be very careful about falling
into this theoretical statements so to
speak that then they deem are true and
applicable to them as well they may see
the suit isn't exactly so see the buddha
said in the scene that is just the scene
okay so in this
that is just the scene yes yeah that's
only true for another hunt yeah so if
you not another hunt for you there is
much more in the scene than just the
scene and yes if you made the effort and
get rid of the more and do the more
understand the more which is understand
the wrong order and thus rectify it then
yes in the scene there has always been
just the scene
so it's true but it's not true to say
when you it's literally saying like oh I
have I have I don't know some I have a
flu whatever I'm sick and the cure for this
whatever I'm sick and the cure for this
sickness is such-and-such and that's it
I'm still sick yeah like are you free
from your sickness on account of knowing
that cure no means it's not a cure means
you don't know enough of it or something
either way the point is to be free from
sickness not to have a theoretical
knowledge of the cure that then you kind
of infer Oh a surprise to me because it
applies to every it's a universal truth
yeah well you're still sick so it is a
universal truth that in the scene
there's just the same it can't be
anything else and it's why when people
jump like you know when the Buddha
talked about the element of Nirvana
it's their present and then people
develop the view
oh so we are already in Ivana yeah cuz
element of Nirvana as in me bonnie is
always present in everyone experience
doesn't matter if you're enlightened or
not it means we are already all in the
bond and welcome to be done exactly so
means we are all already healthy and you
say that while you're still very much
sick and subjected to sickness so I said
theoretical is true but it's completely
wrong for you because you are still sick
and you will remain in the element of
Nibbana but you will not develop an
opponent because you for as long as you
remain sick because then you know so
what is new Barnard in knowing did
Nibbana is the element as in possibility
for every one of us is that the same to
say as oh no you made the effort and
attained and Ivana as a result of it
free from suffering free from conceiving
there so yes a little bit possibility of
Nibbana is there but it doesn't mean
that you have fully developed the actual
abandoned but if you intentionally
trying to obscure the difference between
possible Nibbana which is present and
the extra lebanner which is the possible
manner that has been developed which
means you're free from symptoms on
account of not having developed an
abundant but yes Nibbana is part of
everyone's experience the possibility of
it that's the we referred to today
element of it means yes if you do things
rightly you can actualize that possible
Sun City and so it's not like it's not
like something you create but it's
something you deserve exactly yeah but
that's that's not I'm just pointing out
it or like you know those suitors I
spoke about that recently done the whole
essay on the luminous mind or the mind
is radiant luminous not not inhibited by
anything but it's these gratuitous
defilements that inhibiting so
departments cannot really inhibit the
luminosity of the mind but that's true
for another hand and for somebody who is
free from the defilements then in
hindsight you can know as I said yeah in
hindsight when you arrived at oh so this
is a thought but now the thought that
has uprooted the whole wrong order and
then you realize oh it's still a thought
it could have not been anything else
from the start
yes and you can only say that once you
abandon the wrong water so you can only
say that the mind was truly always
luminous and radiant and uninhibited
once you have abandoned the defilement
of it and the only reason you can
abandon the found and so it is because
they can't truly define the mind the
father mind but it's hard for people to
recognize well theoretically this is
true but practically my situation starts
from the opposite end
so for puta Gina he has to he starts
with the violet it's not true for him to
say that mind is pure
otherwise he'll fall into a view that my
mind is pure regardless of my sickness
and that's why the Buddha when depending
on the context and who he was talking to
he would say like if he talks to
Petrosian about the five aggregates are
about the mind he wouldn't say
for another hand five aggregates have
ceased consciousness is gone
all the aggregates are gone so oh
because yes put two juniors aggregates
which regulates of the wrong road the
only agreed he can know are completely
gone they do not exist as such and and
that's why you it's not always
productive to address things on this
theoretical level because then as I said
somebody who's not free from illness
would understand these things in theory
and then think okay so that's what the
understanding of that is now if you to
now instead it's understood you will be
free from the illness yeah and again if
you know so how does then the mind get
polluted if man cannot be polluted that
is beginningless that mistake of
thinking the pollution thinking the mind
is like this when it can't be like that
is beginningless as the buddha said
there is no first point before which a
vijay wasn't and then the video becomes
the manifest that you can discern it in
other words petitioner and his view was
always as such and that's why wants you
undo it and you recognize the mind could
have not it made no difference to the
mind of the aggregates you're craving
and you do padana yeah could not have
made a difference once you understand
that it's irreversible yeah the author
was always like that
the order was always right matter how
you take care but for you starting point
was the assumption of your own God
that's why you banana is is responsible
for maintenance of the beam of the
reality that you know and and why like
sort of knowledge of these phenomena
he's really just sort of allowing them
to reveal yeah so you remove the
assumption or reality that you know do
you realize the idea state yeah that
once have always been the thoughts in
the scene they have always been just to
seen but he was the whole world of
assumption did I had on top of it and
again that's I mean it's irreversible
once you do it once you remove the
gratuitous as is the Buddha said that
literally that a gang took over is the
word means like superimposed yeah means
can now really become part of it he's
just there adventitious adventitious
once you remove those gratuities
defilements Judas there could not have
been there should not have been there
not knowing that you were placing in
there you remove it they cannot come
back yeah they cannot return because
there is no room for them and that's
where the Buddha meant by opener is not
in the aggregates some part of the
aggregates cannot be positive means 500
don't even know about your Dada yeah you
keep well you can't put it it well this
desire lust means kupatana is there in
regard to the five value because you put
it what I mean is because you put it
there it's there sure that's just that's
the only only thing you know yeah is
that this is there so you have to
acknowledge it first that's a starting
point and not start practice from this
theoretical aspect of aggregates are
already free we are already in a bond
mind is already pure I just need to
scratch through the conventional reality
until I discover the ultimate reality
ultimate is only in response to
conventional so ultimate is determined
by the conventional conventional is
determined by the ultimate either way
you remain ignorant of the nature of
reality of any kind doesn't matter if
its ultimate of conventional reality is
there so the difference is not in
reality and the characteristics of
reality the difference is in the bronco
that you assume in regard to it that's
it and that's not in the conventional
reality no the ultimate reality that's
the political choice division is rock
and then to the widow would say even for
the target ah as far as the language
goes as far as the conventions and
designations go the Tala has understood
it he hasn't blended for his ignorance
and they replaced it with the greater
ultimate reality by removing the veil of
my or something no it stays he still
uses words he still designates what has
changed is the wrong assumption the
wrong order what comes first basically
that's it and the reason what is so hard
to see is because in thought there is
only a thought but which one of those
thoughts thought you put first yeah
thankfully and you realize well
whichever it is it must be wrong because
you're not in our hunt yeah so trying do
the opposite yeah
go against the stream against the grain
yeah so that's like Oh consciousness is
this mind is this thoughts of that
they're all thoughts for you how can you
know consciousness if it's not a thought
yeah how can you know your mind your
mood unless you're thinking it how can
you know your thoughts unless they're
being thought but it's the order of
those things so you can only arrive with
these things in with understanding is if
you arrive at them through the right
order in the same sense in the previous
talk or one of the previous talks we've
done with the you can only know eye
sights and consciousness through the
contact through the pressure so pressure
doesn't disappear when you think about
consciousness eyes don't this pressure
the eyes or get so your pressure is
where the knowledge is of these things
so it's just emphasizing different
aspect within the whole so this is the
same you can't like oh now I'm thinking
about consciousness no you're thinking
about your thoughts mm-hmm and you think
about your thoughts within a mood you
think about the thoughts within a mood
about consciousness so it's always
you're always thinking the same things
which is thoughts mm-hmm it's just
ceasing to assume the you know the
external point of view or do any form of
wrong order
any any manifestation of the wrong order
so what comes first is the thought
within a thought of mood within a
thought of the consciousness and then
you think oh this is just a thought of
conscience and then there is
consciousness thought that you gave a
gratuitous property of being external
real as opposed to this unreal yet
that's another thought that notion of
externality as opposed to insult is
another thought these are not trapped
tracked and if you think that your
escape from it is removing the thought
and you really make tribe forever yes
it's basically just stop assume in the
wrong order that is your freedom they
will remove the symptoms of any illness
disease which and another way of saying
is that whatever can be thought whatever
can be experienced
it depends on something yeah yeah can
you experience anything without the
conscious body being yeah yeah and you
have not seen it did you take into your
consciousness below did you have to pick
and choose your body absolutely not any
difference you can make to the body is
within the body that's given to you yeah
so it's only a secondary difference
so really difference of the fundamental
nature you can only part of the body
yeah yes we can use it what is Paulette
sure yeah but no point it becomes yours
the only reason you can borrow is
because you said so not forgetting that
context for example whatever you do what
anything whatever you feel whatever you
you've done whatever you're planning to
do possibly there and if you it's within
the container of the body being they
given to you conscious body being there
to give it to me I'm not saying it yeah
and learn how to allow that image so to
speak then you're peripherally yeah
without you trying to overly attend it
and get out of it cuz you can't get out
of it you can only forget that you can
only basically drain away your sense of
self within it okay by removing any
notion of the external ownership you
will remove the basis for maintenance of
the sense of self okay because he
doesn't matter
oh I feel like this I feel like that I
feel superior okay I feel inferior and I
feel equal all of that is possible only
because there is this still conscious
body there and I'm not saying it that's
my own sense of self i undermined by
realizing that I cannot own it laughs it
ceases to be myself
so discerning the context and
maintaining the discernment of their
context not attending to the context
you'll be doing that picture send
yourself that's not a contact exactly
once you start attending it ceased to be
the context